A Finding Aid to the Robert Delford Brown Papers, 1964-2009, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Robert Delford Brown papers
1964-2009
Archives of American Art
Brown, Robert Delford
AAA.browrober
Archival Resource Key
3.9 Linear feet
7.98 Gigabytes
The papers of painter, sculptor, and performance artist Robert Delford Brown measure 3.9 linear feet and 7.98 GB and date from 1964-2009. The papers document his career as an artist and in particular the arts space "church" he founded in New York City, known as The First National Church of Exquisite Panic, Inc. The collection consists of biographical material, correspondence, church records, printed and digital material, photographic material, and video records of performance art. Brown's early career is documented in one scrapbook containing photographs, notes, press materials, and select artwork and documentation of ephemeral and performance artworks.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated in 2010 and 2018 by Lynda Roscoe Hartigan who purchased the collection at auction.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical Note
Robert Delford Brown (1930-2009) was a painter, sculptor, and performance artist practicing in New York City, N.Y. Brown was a participant in many art happenings in New York during the 1960s and frequently performed in the persona of a religious leader and founder of his own religion and church, The First National Church of the Exquisite Panic, Inc. which functioned as a community arts space.
Brown was born in Portland, Colorado. His family later moved to Long Beach, California, and he recived bachelor's and master's degrees at University of California, Los Angeles. He began his career as a Surrealist and Abstract Expressionist painter, and in 1959 moved to New York City. In 1963 he married Rhett Cone. While visiting Paris he met the artist Allan Kaprow who encouraged him to participate in a 1964 performance of Karlheinz Stockhausen's "Originale." This performance served as the inspiration for founding The First National Church of Exquisite Panic, Inc. That same year Brown also gained media attention for his "Meat Show," an installation of raw meat which he created in a refrigerated room at the Washington Meat Market in New York City.
In 1967 Brown selected a former New York City branch library as a home for his church and hired Modernist architect Paul Rudolph to redesign the interior. He called the space "The Great Building Crack-Up" and lived there until 1997, hosting art exhibitions, happenings, and preaching his philosophy known as Pharblongence. During Brown's later career he organized many participatory art events, such as "Collaborative Action Gluings." He moved to Houston, Texas in 1997 and later moved to Wilmington, North Carolina, in preparation for a solo exhibition at the Cameron Art Museum in 2008. Robert Delford Brown died in 2009.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter, sculptor, and performance artist Robert Delford Brown measure 3.9 linear feet and 7.98 GB and date from 1964-2009. The papers document his career as an artist and in particular the arts space "church" he founded in New York City, known as The First National Church of Exquisite Panic, Inc. The collection consists of biographical material, correspondence, church records, printed and digital material, photographic material, and video records of performance art. Brown's early career is documented in one scrapbook containing photographs, notes, and press materials.
Biographical material includes a career summary, one diary, one interview transcript, and two interview recordings on videocassette. Correspondence is minimal and includes four letters written by Brown and letters and postcards from others. Printed material consists mostly of books and event announcements documenting Brown's career. Photographs depict his travels in Brazil and China, artwork, and a collaborative event in Paris. Video recordings depict a solo performance art piece and three collaborative performance art events.
Records of the First National Church of Exquisite Panic, Inc. include items produced for events, such as graphics, a t-shirt, "teachings," as well as reproductions of artwork created as part of the church. Also included are founding documents and manifestos.
One scrapbook contains detailed documentation on Brown's career from 1964 to 1974. Included are photographs and press materials for his "Meat Show" event, additional records of the founding of his church, and photographs of various events and happenings at his church. People depicted in the photographs include Brown, Claes Oldenburg, and art critic Mario Amaya, among others.
Artwork includes works on paper incorporating stamps and text from around 2002 to 2008, as well as artwork documentation for ephemeral and performance artworks including Originale (1964), Out of Order Please Use Toilet Down the Hall Across the Lobby (1965), Free Striptease with Drum and Bugle Corps Accompaniment (1966), The Great Building Crack-Up (1967), Mr. Jesus Christ Contest (1972), Turd Forest (1972), and others.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 8 series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1992-2009 (Box 1, 5; 0.7 linear feet, ER01; 2.23 GB)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1970-2009 (Box 1; 4 folders)
Series 3: First National Church of Exquisite Panic, Inc. Records, 1968-2000s (Box 1, 4, 5; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1964-2008 (Box 1-2; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 5: Photographic Material, 1965-2009 (Box 2-3; 1.1 linear feet, ER02; 0.785 GB)
Series 6: Video Recordings of Performance Art, 1994-2005 (Box 3; 0.4 linear feet, ER03-ER05; 4.96 GB)
Series 7: Scrapbook, 1964-1974 (Box 5; 4 folders)
Series 8: Artwork, circa 1965-2008 (Oversize 6-7)
VHS (videotape format); Diaries; Transcripts; Interviews; Video recordings; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Scrapbooks; Photographs; Performance artists -- New York (State) -- New York; Oldenburg, Claes, 1929- -- Photographs; Amaya, Mario
- Biographical Material, 1992-2009; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Box 1, 5; 2.23 Gigabytes ER01
  Scope and Contents note
  Found here are interviews with Robert Delford Brown and a small amount of biographical documentation. Included are a biographical summary which consists of a brief chronology, list of performances, exhibitions, and publications regarding Brown; one diary containing brief daily entries and illustrations; and notes regarding his life written on large sheets of paper. Also found is a transcript of an interview conducted by Robert C. Morgan; videocassette recordings of an interview conducted by Francesco Conz in Verona, Italy; and recordings of an interview, "I'm a Sweet Old Man Now," conducted by Mark Bloch for Panscan TV.
  - Biographical Summary, circa 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diary, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Essay, "The Strange Case of Robert Delford Brown (a.k.a. Saint Kittenish), Iconoclast-Part II," by Robert C. Morgan, circa 2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Interview Transcript, 2003 April 8; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - "Conz Interview," Edited Master, 2002; Archival Resource Key; (1 original videocassette: Betacam, 3 duplicate videocassettes: VHS) (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
  - "Conz Interview," Unedited Footage, 2002; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (Betacam) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "I'm a Sweet Old Man Now: A Visit with Robert Delford Brown at the Great Building Crackup", 1997; Archival Resource Key; (1 original Videocassettes (VHS), 1 duplicate Videocassettes (VHS)); Includes born-digital records, see ER01 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - "I'm a Sweet Old Man Now: A Visit with Robert Delford Brown at the Great Building Crackup", 1979, Digital Video Recording, 2006; Archival Resource Key; 2.23 Gigabytes One computer file (Folder ER01)
    Scope and Contents
    Duplicate of video in Box 1, Folders 10-11
  - Obituary, 2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Project Proposal, 2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Notes, 2003 December 16; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1970-2009; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 1
  Correspondence consists of four letters written by Robert Delford Brown, letters to Brown from art dealer Eugenia Butler, and a series of postcards from artist Victoria Schultz. Also found are digital scans and printed copies of illustrated letters from friend and fellow artist H. C. Westermann.
  - Letters Written by Robert Delford Brown, circa 2004-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters from Eugenia Butler, 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters from H. C. Westermann (Digital Copies), 1970-1971; 2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Postcards from Victoria Schultz, 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
- First National Church of Exquisite Panic, Inc. Records, 1968-2000s; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Box 1, 4, 5
  Found here are records and items produced as part of Brown's First National Church of Exquisite Panic, Inc. Included are a certificate of incorporation, seal, various written manifestos and doctrines of the church, as well as signs, graphics, and ephemera used as part of the performances and public events. Also found are reproductions and documentation regarding Brown's series of artwork called "Anoter Map to Navada," created as part of his church's philosophies, as well as sheets of paper with "teachings" written in black marker.
  - "Another Map to Nevada" Series, 2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - Book, Ikons of the First National Church of Exquisite Panic, Inc., circa 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Certificate of Incorporation, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Manifesto, Statements, and Doctrines, circa 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Signs and Graphics, 1990s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
    Oversized items housed in box 5, folder 1
  - Stock Certificates, circa 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Tax Document, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Teachings", 2003 January 18; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "Teachings", circa 2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - T-Shirt, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
  - Corporate Seal, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
  - Buttons and Stickers, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
  - Oversized Signs and Graphics, 1990s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Oversized items from box 1, folders 23-24
- Printed Material, 1964-2008; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Printed material primarily consists of books. Of note are books on Brown's "Collaborative Action Gluings" and "First Class Portraits," as well as a 1992 Fluxus event. Also found is an announcement for his 1964 "Meat Show" installation. One folder of miscellaneous printed material contains fliers, brochures, and exhibition announcements.
  - Announcement for "Meat Show", 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Collaborative Action Gluings: Robert Delford Brown, 2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - First Class Portraits by Robert Delford Brown, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Flux-Flag, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Operating Manual for Spaceship Earth by R. Buckminster Fuller (Photocopy), 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - A Pictographic History of the Oglala Sioux, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - RE/Search # 11: Pranks!, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1973; circa 2004-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Photographic Material, 1965-2009; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 1.1 Linear feet Box 2-3; 0.785 Gigabytes ER02
  The bulk of the photographs found here depict Brown's trips to Brazil and China. Also found are photographs labeled as depicting a collaborative art project with artist Victoria Schultz and others in Paris. Slides and digital photographs depict these same subjects as well as Brown's artwork. Also of note are black and white photographs of the interior of "The Great Building Crack-Up." Researchers should note that many additional photographs are included in Series 7: Scrapbook.
  - Robert Delford Brown, circa 2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Brazil, 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9-17)
  - Brazil - Negatives, 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
  - Cats, 1980s-1990s; 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - China, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22-26)
  - China - Negatives, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - "Collaboration with Victoria Schultz and two other women - Paris", circa 2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Events, 1990s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4-8)
  - Great Building Crack-Up, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Porto Allegre" Negatives and Slides, circa 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Slides, circa 1980s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11-16)
  - Digital Photographs, 1998-2009; Archival Resource Key; 0.785 Gigabytes 90 computer files (Folder ER02)
- Video Recordings of Performance Art, 1994-2005; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 3; 4.96 Gigabytes ER03-ER05
  Video recordings depict solo and collaborative performance art events created by Robert Delford Brown. Included is a recording of a solo performance art piece "Fried Blood." Three collaborative performance art events involved gathering the public, primarily children, to participate in activities such as pumpkin carving, balloon paintings, and creating a collaged environment out of paper.
  - Performance Art by Robert Delford Brown, "Fried Blood", 1994 May 27; Archival Resource Key; (1 original videocassette: U-Matic, 1 duplicate videocassette: Betacam); Contains born-digital materials, see ER03 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - "Fried Blood" (1994); "Martian Outpost" (1998), Digital Video Recording, 2005; Archival Resource Key; 2.83 Gigabytes One computer file (Folder ER03)
    Duplicate of a film in Box 3, Folders 19-20, and a film in Box 3, Folders 22-24.
  - Collaborative Performance Art, Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
    - "Balloonatic Action Balloonary" (2005 March 3), Digital Video Recording, Archival Resource Key; 1 Gigabyte One computer file (Folder ER04)
    - "Martian Outpost", 1998 April 14; Archival Resource Key; (1 videocassette: Hi8, 1 duplicate videocassette: Betacam); Contains born-digital records, see ER03 (Box 3, Folder 22-24)
    - "Pumpkin Carving", Digital Video Recording, 2004; Archival Resource Key; 1.13 Gigabytes One computer file (Folder ER05)
- Scrapbook, 1964-1974; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 5
  One large scrapbook contains documentation on Robert Delford Brown's art events, happenings, and environments from 1964 to 1974. A large portion of the scrapbook documents the "Meat Show" event that Brown created in 1964. Found here are photographs of the installation, press materials, and a list of supplies needed. Also included in the scrapbook are photographs depicting Brown working on projects, events, people such as Claes Oldenburg and Mario Amaya, and interior and exterior views of "The Great Building Crack-Up." Additionally, there are newspaper and magazine clippings, press releases, event announcements, scattered letters, and documentation on the founding of The First National Church of Exquisite Panic, Inc.
  Arrangement note
  Scrapbook materials have been removed from the original album and housed in archival folders. The original order of the documents has been maintained.
  - Scrapbook, 1964-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3-6)
- Artwork, circa 1965-2008; Series 8; Archival Resource Key
  Artwork includes works on paper incorporating stamps and text from around 2002 to 2008, as well as artwork documentation for ephemeral and performance artworks including Originale (1964), Out of Order Please Use Toilet Down the Hall Across the Lobby (1965), Free Striptease with Drum and Bugle Corps Accompaniment (1966), The Great Building Crack-Up (1967), Mr. Jesus Christ Contest (1972), Turd Forest (1972), and others.
  - Works on Paper, circa 2002-2008; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 6)
  - Artwork Documentation Posters, circa 1965-1975; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 7)